<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the Cathedral Church of St. Canice Kilkenny, Feb. 27. 1669. By Joseph Teate, dean of St. Can. Kilkenny</title>
            <author>Teate, Joseph.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64289</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219172</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830686</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64289)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2081:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the Cathedral Church of St. Canice Kilkenny, Feb. 27. 1669. By Joseph Teate, dean of St. Can. Kilkenny</title>
                  <author>Teate, Joseph.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 16, 25-56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Benjamin Tooke, printer to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty, and are to be sold by Mary Crooke, in Castle-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an imprimatur leaf dated: July 19. 1670.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the CATHEDRAL CHURCH OF S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> CANICE KILKENNY, <hi>Feb.</hi> 27. 1669.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>JOSEPH TEATE,</hi> Dean of St. CAN. KILKENNY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſty, and are to be ſold by <hi>Mary Crooke,</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:35139:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>P. M.</hi> Archiepiſcopo <hi>Dublinienſi à Sac.</hi> Domeſt.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 19. 1670.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35139:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Lady, EMILIA, Counteſs of OSSORY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Divine Law that conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes Tribute the due of Princes, hath conſigned Honour the due of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: which by the Learned is diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed into <hi>Civil,</hi> which is a Deſcent from worthy Anceſtors: <hi>Moral,</hi> whoſe Spring
<pb facs="tcp:35139:3"/> is Virtue: and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> which conſiſts in a New Birth, whereby we are Co-heirs with Chriſt, and the Off-ſpring of God.</p>
            <p>Madam, I judge my ſelf as inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as Envy can do impertinent, to think by Elogies of your Merit, to add Luſtre to your Name; your Ladiſhip ſtands upon ſuch a Theatre, that every Scene of your life is expoſed to Publique View, and therefore if I ſhould give flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Titles, the Suffrage of men would ſoon condemn me; but where God hath made me a Debtor, it is but juſt to make Payment in conſcience to the higheſt Sanction, and Sence of my own Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gratitude. How your Ladiſhip is enobled by Birth, I ſhall relate in the words of the Learned <hi>Voſſius,</hi> who in his Book of the three Creeds, Dedicated to <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Aurange,</hi> tells us, that his Deſcent was from <hi>Adolphus</hi> of <hi>Naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw Ceſar</hi> in the twelfth Century, ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:35139:3"/> Madam, by your Bloud, and Allyes, you are a Branch circling from an Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Stem of Majeſty.</p>
            <p>But Madam, the Nobility of your Deſcent, onely enrolls your Name in the Catalogue of the Great, is Secular and Tranſitory, Calculated for this World; but it is your Grace and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that writes it in the Book of Life, and Embalms it to Immortality; the Wreaths of civil Honour are withering, Grandeur is fugitive, but Godlineſs is a Crown that fadeth not away: which conſiſts in a great Humility, conſtant Devotion, and a diffuſive Charity, which were the Amabilities of your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips Converſation among us; ſo that you have left behind you a Good Name, and carried with you a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>To digeſt juſt praiſes, is a tender, and diſcreet Virtue, that therefore you may give the Glory to God, I ſhall turn a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick
<pb facs="tcp:35139:4"/> into a Prayer, That your Soul may be precious in the ſight of God, as the Apple of his Eye, the Signet on his Right hand, and be made up among his Jewells, That the Loſſes of your greateſt temporal Bleſſings may be borne with Patience, and what God hath ſpared, may be enjoyed with Moderation; that your mind may be equal, and fixed in the great Accidents, and Viciſſitudes of humane Life, that the Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may prove to your Ladiſhip a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Iſland, by becoming what it once was called, an Iſland of Saints.</p>
            <p>This Sermon had been ſooner made publick, but that it was retarded by a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſickneſs; when it was preached, it was conſecrated to God, and now its printed, its dedicated to your Ladiſhip, by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips moſt humble Servant <hi>JOSEPH TEATE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35139:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 TIM 3.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Having a form of Godlineſs, but denying the power thereof.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SAint <hi>Paul</hi> who was not a whit behind the chiefeſt Apoſtles in Languages, Labours, Gifts of healing, Viſions, Extaſies, and Prophetick Inſpirations, foretells us, what monſtrous impieties the Womb of time ſhould travell with under the diſpenſation of the Goſpel; He foreſaw the wickedneſs of men flying on, as faſt as the wings of time could car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it: That as the Dew of Heaven, and Showres of Divine bleſſings ſhould deſcend in plenty and abundance, ſo the Inundation of iniquity ſhould riſe higher to deluge and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow the world, that times ſhould be as perillous, as ſins were exceeding ſinfull: Therefore as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35139:5"/> a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt, not ignorant of the devices and ſtratagems of his ſpiritual enemies, he preſents us with a Liſt of their Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions; ſuch a Catalogue of Vices that may exerciſe our patience to recite, as well as reſiſt them: where ſelfe love leads the Van, and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie in Religion brings up the Rear; And prefixeth this Aſterisk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do thou turn Gnoſtick in this, Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> and know that <hi>the laſt dayes ſhall be evil, for men ſhall be Traytors, Truce-breakers, Heady, High-minded, Lovers of pleaſures, more then Lovers of God, having a form, but denying the power of Godlineſs.</hi> The Ages ſubſequent to the Apoſtle have given a completion to his Propheſie, that no Fraud is ſo inſinuating as that which is pious, no Error ſo infectious as that which is formal, when the Devil tells Lyes in Hypocriſie from under the Mantle of a Prophet, they are credited as the Oracles of God, and men think they entertain Celeſtial Immiſſions, when he ſuggeſteth things that ſeem to ſavour of piety as an Angel of light. <hi>Valentinus</hi> preach'd zealouſly, <hi>Arius</hi> repented publickly, <hi>Pelagius</hi> lived piouſly; yet they were a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umvirate of the moſt pernicious Hereticks that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35139:5"/> ever troubled the Church, when a man of Parts, and Eloquence, who deſigns Schiſm in the Church, and ſedition in the State comes up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pulpit with a glorious Profeſſion, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies his induſtry in the converſion of Souls, and ſeems himſelf to be in an Agony, when he talks of our Saviour; his mortified counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance enlivens his Projects, his Perſon is had in admiration, his Diſcourſes received with credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, as the Babilonians entertain'd <hi>Zopyrus,</hi> who by ſhewing them his mangled members made himſelf Maſter of their Affections, and ſoon after <hi>Darius</hi> Lord of their City.</p>
            <p>So ſad is the Truth, that as the moſt poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous pills may be guilded, ſo the vileſt impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may be garniſhed with a ſhew of Religion: as may appear from thoſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> mentions <hi>verſe</hi> 2. <hi>Covetous, Boaſters, Proud, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> &amp;c. A man may be Covetous in his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>Judas</hi> may aske why the Oyntment was not ſold and given to the poor, not that he cared for the poor, but becauſe he was a Thief, a man may be a Boaſter in his ſelf-denial, with the Philoſopher write a Treatiſe againſt Vain-glory, and ſubſcribe to it with his own Name; Proud in his humility, like <hi>Diotrophes</hi> preach
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35139:6"/> the Goſpel and affect Preheminence, or <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> revile the Grandure of Princes with greater inſolence, a Blaſphemer in his prayers crying as the <hi>Phariſee, God, I thank thee, that I am not as other men are,</hi> and for all that be worſe, and take his name in vain: There hath not been an irreverend Perſon in the Aſſembly, a diſloyal Perſon to Authority, a ſchismatical Seperatiſt from the Church: no, not the Murder of Gods Prophets, and Gods Anoynted, nor any ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Alienation of their Eſtates, and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, nor the Blaſphemies of Quakers, Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Familiſts, but have been uſhered in with the hideous out-cryes of Repentance and Reformation: there is not a ſinner in the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, but may have the <hi>form of Godlineſs, and deny the power thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The terms of the propoſition to be explained are four: <hi>Godlineſs, the Form of Godlineſs, the Power, the Denying the power under the Form of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> if we conſult the Etymon, the <hi>Helleniſts</hi> will tell us, is derived from a verb that ſignifies to worſhip, and imports that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Reverence a Creature oweth his Maker, and that in the dayes of <hi>Moſes</hi> he was called a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35139:6"/> Godly perſon, that was a Proſelyte of the Gate, acknowledged and ador'd a Deity, obſerved the ſeven precepts of the ſons of <hi>Noah,</hi> with <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> and the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Eunuch. But the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of it conſiſts in the Latitude of Holineſs, the Rectitude and Conformity of the heart, and life to the firſt and ſecond Tables of the Law; Godlineſs is profitable to all things, that is obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to that Law that is holy in its Precept, juſt in its Penalties, and good in its Rewards. Yet in other places of theſe Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy,</hi> it is to be underſtood in a more limited ſenſe, ſometimes for the Syſteme of fundamental truths, call'd the Doctrine according to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Symbol of which the Apoſtle gives us, when he ſaith, <hi>Great is the myſtery of Godlineſs. God manifeſted in the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. Sometimes for the Duties of Religion, diſtinct from the Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of honeſt men, ſo we are exhorted <hi>to live peaceable, and quiet lives in Godlineſs, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty,</hi> but here being oppoſed to a <hi>Form,</hi> an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Pomp and Pageantry, it is the inward Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Devotion of the heart, whereby God is worſhipped in Spirit without Carnality, and in Truth without Hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The form of Godlineſs,</hi> is its Scheme; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35139:7"/> external Similitude, a Faſhion, and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, or appearance of that which is not real and intrinſical. As <hi>Jupiter</hi> among the Poets was metamorphoſed into the ſhape of a Beaſt, though he pretended to be a Deity; ſo theſe men would pretend to be Deities, when they are but Beaſts, the word beings <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Eſſential <hi>Form</hi> cannot be here intended, which is ſo far from the denial of Godlineſs, that it gives it Difference and Operation, as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soul is the form of a man, whereby he diſcourſeth, and is diſtinguiſhed from all other Ranks of Beings, ſo the Image of God is the <hi>Form of Godlineſs</hi> that gives it Power, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction from all things that are not homogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to it. But that form which conſiſts in a Cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of accidents, and is the more Vain and and void, as the Text is excellent, on which it is a Gloſs, and Paraphraſe: ſo <hi>Eſau</hi> who was under the Curſe of the Creation to bring forth Briars, and Thorns, being an hairy and rough man, in the form and apparel of <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſeem'd a Paradiſe, and ſmelled like a Field which the Lord had bleſſed: ſo a common perſon in a Comedy may repreſent the Majeſty of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. But then theſe Forms are like the Idea's
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35139:7"/> of <hi>Plato,</hi> wholy abſtracted from matter, and deſtitute of the <hi>power of Godlineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This power of Godlineſs</hi> is, when the Habits of Grace ſend forth the vigorous and vital Actings of holyneſs, as the Fountain doth Streams, and the Sun Rayes and Emanations of light, as will appeare in the ſequel of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>Men deny the <hi>power</hi> under the <hi>form of Godlineſs</hi> when they ſeem to be Pious, becauſe they are Politick, and profeſs themſelves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians becauſe Subjects to a King that is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith; yet think, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Holineſs of the Law, is but the Severity of Melancholick Men, who have repreſented Chriſt to be an hard Maſter, and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they invocate his Name are diſloyal to his Commands, profeſs they know God, but in works Deny him; ingeminate an oral Loyalty, crying <hi>Lord, Lord, but do not his will:</hi> and ſo think to palliat the Atheiſm of their lives by the Religion of their Language: Thus the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis and Important Terms of the <hi>Propoſition</hi> are explained.</p>
            <p>We might juſtly expect, when an Apoſtle is giving us the Kalander and Ephimerides of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35139:8"/> Times of the <hi>Meſsias;</hi> that the firſt Proſpect in the Firmament of the Church, would be an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon of hope, the diſpenſation of the Goſpel being ſo bright and bleſſed, <hi>When the Sun of righteouſneſs did appear with healing in his wings;</hi> yet he preſageth nothing, but Clouds, and Darkneſs, Eclipſes of that light that ſhould ſhine before many, glaring, and portentous Phai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena's, and the Signes of Heaven without Celeſtial Influences: <hi>in the laſt dayes perillous times ſhall come, Laſt dayes</hi> they are in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the adminiſtration, that doth ſucceed, and exceed that which was Levitical, Chriſt being a better Prince then <hi>Moſes</hi> in his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, a better Prieſt then <hi>Aaron</hi> in his Sacrifice, he was not onely an High Prieſt, but an Apoſtle, that was ſent out of the Boſome of the Father, to bring glad tydings, yet when the Plenty of Grace was moſt of all diſperſed, the <hi>Power of Godlineſs</hi> was moſt deſpiſed, ſo that men were efferated by clemency, enraged by meekneſs, impatient by forbearance, wax wanton in the moſt goodly Heritage; and live as if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were an hard Maſter in the Largeſs of his Bounty. <hi>For in the laſt dayes, men ſhall be Lovers of themſelves, having a form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35139:8"/> but denying the power thereof:</hi> So that firſt the <hi>Form,</hi> and then the <hi>Power,</hi> are the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of my preſent Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Form</hi> may be conſidered as a Virgin, or a Proſtitute, as abſtracted from, or concomitant upon the powers of Religion, as <hi>Diana</hi> was in Heaven a ſtar, but in Hell a firebrand, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of <hi>Pluto;</hi> ſo a <hi>form</hi> flowing from the <hi>power of Godlineſs,</hi> is Angelical, but diveſted from it, Diabolical.</p>
            <p>For when our Works of Darkneſs appear as Angels of Light, we mock God, by honouring him with our Lips, and dethroning him from our Hearts, we crucifie the Lord of Glory; and, as the Souldiers, put a Crown on his Head, and Robes on his body, and ſalute him with an Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Hail King of the Jews;</hi> we worſhip the true God, as if he were an Idol, that had eyes, and ſaw not, not conſidering his great Attribute of ſearching the heart; we make God abhor his own Inſtitutions, and reverſe his Laws, <hi>bring no more vain Oblations, incenſe is an abomination to me,</hi> as if he would receive no Honour from the Services of Hypocrites, but what he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trains for by his publick Judgements; Thus a <hi>form</hi> is a deſperate Incentive to, and a plauſible
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35139:9"/> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of the greateſt Villanies; <hi>Cain</hi> firſt Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to his God, and then ſlaughtered his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Jezabel</hi> inſtitutes a Faſt, and then thirſts for the Blood of <hi>Naboth.</hi> The <hi>ſtrange Woman</hi> paid her vowes with Peace-offerings in her hands, and then managed the Artifices of an Adultereſs, and entred into Obſcene Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of defiling her husbands Bed. The Jews conſecrated Gifts to the Treaſury of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and then cryed, <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are we,</hi> but the <hi>Corban</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bethel</hi> the Houſe of God, into <hi>Bethaven</hi> an Houſe of Affliction, to their indigent, and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved Parents. Thus a Formaliſt makes the Rites of Religion, a Gloſs for ſin, ſollicits wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in the external glorifications of God, and is like thoſe ſort of Meteors, that ſhine onely in their fall from heaven.</p>
            <p>But a <hi>Form,</hi> in conjunction with the <hi>Power,</hi> is an Ornament of great Price in the ſight of God; St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not diſcourage a form, that is modeſt in Complexion, grave in Geſture, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet in the Expreſſions of it ſelf; that waits on the <hi>Power of Godlineſs,</hi> as a Diſciple on his Maſter, or a Servant on his Lord; as he ſaith in the firſt Epiſtle, <hi>Good works become women, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35139:9"/> Godlineſs;</hi> Religion is not to be like thoſe <hi>mineral mountains</hi> that appear barren, when the Veins of Gold lodge in their Bowells, but as the <hi>Kings daughter, all glorious within, yet her Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of wrought Gold.</hi> Can a Maid forget her ornaments? or a Bride her attire? or the Spouſe of Chriſt her Rayment of Needle-work? as <hi>David</hi> invited all his faculties within him, ſo his Glory, his Tongue, to joyn in the Chorus, as the moſt natural, proper, and muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby an heart, Big with the Burden in the ſongs of Praiſe, could beſt deliver it ſelf; <hi>our Lights are ſo to ſhine before men, that they ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our good works, may glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The corruption of this <hi>form,</hi> is either Groſs, and Phariſaical, when men are Zealots for the firſt Table, for the Temple, and Invocation, for Sacrifices and Altars, for Incenſe, and Oblation, Sabbaths, and ſolemn Feaſts; but break in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſecond, neither ſparing their neighbours Wives in Luſt, nor their Lives in their Anger, nor their Eſtates in their Avarice, nor their Good Names in their Ambition; as if the two Tables were as the two Principles, and Gods of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> the one Good, and the other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35139:10"/> Evil; the firſt Table a Sacred Edict, a Royal Promulgation to be kept, the ſecond to be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated as a Snare, and Tyrannical Exaction.</p>
            <p>The other corruption is Subtile and Moral, when a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> and Honeſty do meet together and Kiſs each other; A man may be born in the Pale of the Church, baptized into the moſt holy faith, inſtructed in her Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes, and Homilies, And only be a Patriot of Virtue in the profeſſion of Faith: he may ſtand up at the recitation of the Creed, and ſay Amen to every Article, and yet be juſt in his actions, temperate in his life, generous in his ſpirit, upon no other principles then <hi>Socrates</hi> or <hi>Seneca</hi> might be, his Religious Duties are all Moralities, he reads the ſcripture and entertains them with an humane Faith, as the ſtories of <hi>Zenophon,</hi> or <hi>Plutarch,</hi> he gives to the Poor and calls it Charity, when his Almes are the Iſſues of a natural Compaſſion, and Benignity, what he doth is from the Dictates of Reaſon, which are perfective of the humane nature, not from an aſſent to a divine Revelation, or Obedience to the will of God: Now Virtue in a Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Godlineſs is the higheſt ſemblance of Grace, I cannot perſwade my ſelf that the light
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35139:10"/> of nature that convinceth Atheiſm, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates on the Omnipotence and Wiſdom of God is an <hi>ignis fatuus;</hi> or that the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that God hath written in the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as well as the hearts of all men is a Throne of Iniquity, or that Honeſty, Temperance, Chaſtity and Juſtice are glittering ſins, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beleive that they are Rudiments of our Creation, not wholy Obliterated by the fall of man though they do not pleaſe God in that way of Complacency that faith doth; they may be Strictures, and darker Shaddowes, though Graces are the Bright and Orient Colours in that Soul that is created after Gods image: To apply all this, if a man profeſſeth himſelf a Chriſtian, and is only Chaſt as a Brave <hi>Romane,</hi> out of Glory, or a Mind cultivated by Reaſon, none can reſolve the Sophiſm, and ſay that his Virtue doth not flow from the influences of faith, but the infallibility of Heaven, and his own Conſcience. <hi>The Formes of Godlineſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then skilfull to deceive, I ſhall abſolve my diſcourſe in two particulars. Firſt in ſhewing Reaſons why <hi>Godlineſs</hi> will expreſs it ſelf in a <hi>Form,</hi> then Rules to direct the <hi>Form</hi> by the <hi>Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35139:11"/>
               <head>Reaſons why <hi>Godlineſs</hi> hath a <hi>Form:</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The nature of Graces is to be active in the Diſcovery of it ſelf; The Spirit of God is no where more Rhetorical then in the Variety of Metaphors on this Subject, He calls it a <hi>Light that muſt ſhine before men,</hi> that may as eaſily be ſuppreſſed in its Heat, as conceal'd in its Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; He compares it to the vital moyſture of <hi>a Tree planted by the Rivers of water, that ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth its Bloſſoms and Fruits in due ſeaſon;</hi> to <hi>Leaven,</hi> whoſe Fermentation continues <hi>till it hath Leavened the whole Lump: to perfumed Garments;</hi> the <hi>ſmel</hi> of <hi>Lebanon;</hi> and the <hi>Powders</hi> of the <hi>Merchants;</hi> ſuch an Impulſe there is in Grace to diſplay its own Glory; So it was with St. <hi>Paul</hi> who was to beare the name of Chriſt before Kings, ſaith he, <hi>I beleived, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have I ſpoken and in St. Peter</hi> who bare the name of Chriſt before the <hi>Sanedrim; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſpeake the things we have ſeen, and heard.</hi> when <hi>David</hi> muſed, the Fire burned, but it flamed forth when he ſpake, out of the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his heart; with the <hi>heart</hi> a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiveth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35139:11"/> unto <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and with the <hi>tongue Confeſſion</hi> is made unto <hi>Salvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſenſe of thoſe great Priviledges, and divine Relations we have by Godlineſs excites us to it, if we are a choſen Generation, a Royal Preiſt-hood, a Holy Nation, and Peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; it is to ſhew forth the Praiſes of him that called us; ſo <hi>David</hi> that was a choſen Prince, a Royal Prophet, a Peculiar Perſon did; <hi>Come and heare all ye that fear God, and I will tell you what he hath done for my Soul;</hi> it is not proper for that Soul that is Loud in begging mercyes, to be Silent, when it receives them: God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered my Darling from the Paw of the Lyon, redeemed me from ſin, reſcued me from Satan, ranſomed me from the Bottomleſs Pit, and with a greater depth of Love, hath invited me with glorious Liberties, made me a member of his Son, equal to the Angels, an Heir of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and if I am ſtill ſilent, I muſt implead his goodneſs, becauſe it is unutterable, and my own joy that is unſpeakable, and full of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>It is Gods end in giving Graces, that their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſick Worth and Luſtre may ſhine forth, to his own Glory, and the Good of others, we are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35139:12"/> filled with the fruits of Righteouſneſs, to the praiſe, and glory of God; and hereby is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorifyed, if we bring forth much fruit: Grace loſeth that advantage of its Influence, and Exemplarity, when it is a candle put under a buſhel, which it hath, when all the Graces ſhine as a Branch of lights to the whole houſe: when faith leads a Monaſtick Life, is an Hermit in Solitudes, and agitates devout meditations in a private Boſome; it is an incloſed Garden in a Wilderneſs, it gives pleaſure to a contemplative Life; but it ſeems not to work by Love in the feeling of Communion, by caſting Beams on the Members of that Body, whoſe Head is Chriſt: a <hi>Form</hi> then is acceptable to God, being ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Communion of Saints, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to the Honour of his own Name.</p>
               <p>God requires the ſervice and ſubjection of the whole man, the Life and the Language, the Mind, and the Mouth, the Faculties of the Soul, and the Organs of the Body to glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gratitude to God, and Charity to our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, engage us to a <hi>Form of Godlineſs;</hi> the firſt makes us ſpeak Honourable things of God, the ſecond thing Neceſſary for Man; Inſtruction
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35139:12"/> to the ignorant, Reproofe to the vicions, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the diſconſolate, when the Channels of the divine ſpirit are as open, as the Fountaine is free and Feſtival; As the Beneficence of God to the body and ſoul requireth the integrity of the whole man, who hath created and bleſſed both; So he hath created and bleſſed the Body in that Dependance on, and Communion with the Soul, that while there is Humility in the Heart, it will bend the knee in adoration; where there is deſire in the Reines, it will lift up the Hands in unceſſant Supplications; where there is Joy in the Mind, it will open the Mouth to ſhew forth its praiſe.</p>
               <p>Our Baptiſmal Vow doth oblige us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Faith of Chriſt crucified, which in the dayes of Perſecution was an eminent act of Fortitude and reſolution, Chriſt crucified was to the <hi>Jewes</hi> a Stumbling Block, and to the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſs; yet <hi>Lactantius</hi> tells us that the Primitive Chriſtians had the ſigne of the Croſs drawn on their Fore-heads in moſt orient Blood, to perſwade Infidels to beleive that they were built upon the Jewiſh Stumbling ſtone, and dignified with the Grecian obloquy. The beauty of a <hi>Form</hi> is commended to us by theſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35139:13"/> Perſwaſions; as the Glorious Attire of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; yet this Attire is to be fitted and adapted to the power; I ſhall therefore ſuperadde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rules to direct the <hi>Form</hi> by the <hi>Power.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Have no collateral Reſpect, or Siniſter Deſign at thine own honour, advantage, or reputation in thy Profeſſions, and <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs;</hi> It is an Argument of a low, and a looſe, a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinary and a diſingenuous ſpirit, for a man to pretend Gods Glory when he intends his own; God will have it all to himſelf, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence; we are to lay down our Carnal Excellencies, when we take up a Spiritual Profeſſion. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gloried not in his own Labours, but in the Love of God, <hi>I laboured more then they all, yet not I but the grace of God that is in me; I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me:</hi> much like that Expreſſion when he tells us, that when he doth what he hates, <hi>it is not I, but ſin that dwelleth in me;</hi> So that as to his perſonal condition, when the ſum total is caſt up as to Grace, and Concupiſcence, it amounts but to two Ciphers ſet one againſt another, as he doth juſtly excuſe his Infirmities, ſo he doth modeſtly refuſe the honour due unto his Graces.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35139:13"/>
               <p>Avoid all conceited Tones, affected Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, and Antick Geſtures in thy Profeſſion, and <hi>Form of Godlineſs;</hi> theſe Ridiculous things are ſufficiently confuted by a mimical Deriſion; for there is a Behaviour becoming Holineſs; when we Profeſs as Saints, we ſhould Act as Men; ſome move in an higher Sphere, and place Religion in the frequent Repetitions of Jeſus Chriſt, and the holy Spirit of God, when they have luſciouſly ingeminated theſe names, which are onely to be mentioned with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and Trembling, they think they have witneſſed a good Confeſſion; but ſome are para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, and vilifie all things that are not a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Revelation, and a Lofty Language, as the <hi>Valentinians,</hi> in <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> deſpiſed the uſual Dialects of other men, uſing Exotick Idioms, the bold, and boaſting phraſes of <hi>Barbarians;</hi> ſuch we meet with in the diſcourſes of <hi>Jacob Behman,</hi> and <hi>Van Helmont;</hi> in the inſcriptions, and pages of the books of <hi>Quakers,</hi> which they call the boſom of God, the outward openings of inward ſhuttings, Godded with God, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with Chriſt, beams of approaching glory. Theſe ſwelling words of vanity are unknown to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35139:14"/> the Scripture, and contrary to the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Let not the <hi>Form</hi> exceed the <hi>Power,</hi> or be as the <hi>Shadows</hi> of the Evening, Longer then the ſubſtances on which they do depend. <hi>Virgil</hi> gives ſeveral ſigns of an approaching night, That then the Toads begin to croak, and crawl about; The Shepherds return home, and the Shadows of the Mountains grow Long. Have we not had theſe ill Symptoms, that our day is far ſpent? doe not Sectaries meet together in Numbers? Are not ſome Paſtors ſuſpended from executing their Charge? is not the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Darkneſs highly advanced? we may gueſs it to be Midnight by the Dreams and Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and pretended Viſions of ſome <hi>Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſts.</hi> Our Saviour condemned the Generation of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that curtail'd the Law, and made broad their Phylacteries; who when they Faſted, disfigured their faces by diſtorted Mouths, and penſive Countenances, as if defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity were the <hi>Form of Godlineſs.</hi> Suffer not the <hi>form</hi> to be of equal Extenſion with the <hi>power,</hi> becauſe it is apt to Degenerate, and become Exceſſive. There are ſome eminent Devotions, that are as the Sun in the Meridian, the Shadows
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35139:14"/> are ſmall; and they enter into a Cloſet, as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs from humane Obſervations, and there are Humiliations, wherein we are to anoint our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to make them Shine, and when they ſhine, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, we are to veyl them, though it be by an Irradiation from God. We are inſtructed to this by the Windows of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, that were narrow outwards, but broad within, and Receptive of light, by the Temple it ſelf, that was conſpicuous indeed without, but the Guildings and Magnificences were internal, by the Sanctuary that was Veiled, but within were the Altar, and Oracle, the Propitiatory and Mercy-Seat, the Cherubims, and God that dwelt between them; by the Heavens, whoſe Appearance to the Earth is an azure Canopy, emboſs't with Clouds, and glittering ſtars, but within there is God, and Jeſus the Mediator of a new Covenant, an innumerable Company of Angels, and the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, that reign with him in immortal, and everlaſting Glory.</p>
               <p>Let thy <hi>form</hi> keep a conſtant Tenour in heavy, as well as Halcion dayes; when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> flouriſhed in the dayes of <hi>Alexander,</hi> the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans</hi> worſhipped at her Temple, and came
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35139:15"/> to warm themſelves at the High Preiſts fire; but when <hi>Antiochus</hi> had Ranſackt the City, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Treaſuries, then they bleſſed themſelves at mount <hi>Gerizim</hi> in the Denyal of the God of Iſrael: when Chriſt multiplyed the Loaves he multiplyed his followers, who would have taken him by force and made him King; They thought his Territoryes would be Opulent, his Feilds and Vineyards fertile, that his Jewiſh Subjects needed not to travel to Egypt in the dayes of Famine, but that his Monarchy would infinitely exceed that of <hi>Solomons</hi> in Peace and Plenty; They thought that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Eagles would be gathered as Chickens un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Wings, and that his Gleanings would be better then the Vintage of all the Kingdomes upon Earth; But when he told them, <hi>his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was not of this World;</hi> that his <hi>Crown muſt be of Thorns,</hi> how few did bear his reproach to follow him without the Camp? to honour him in the indignities of his paſſion? What is this but the Artifice of filthy Lucre, to make a Gain of Godlineſs to aſſemble for Corn, Wine, and Oyl, to bake Cakes to the Queen of heaven, not to be conſumed with famine; to court the Kings Daughter becauſe ſhe is an Inheritrix of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35139:15"/> temporal Bleſſings, and not for the Beauties of her Holineſs; but they that are affraid, or aſhamed of the Profeſſion of Godlineſs before Tyrants, Tribunals, Flames, and Faggots, of them will the Son of Man be aſhamed, when he comes in the glory of the Father, with all his holy Angels.</p>
               <p>Let thy <hi>Form</hi> have ſuch an inviting Modeſty, as to allure others to a Love and Participation of the <hi>Power of Godlineſs.</hi> Muſitians obſerve in the Sympathy of ſounds, that if two Viols be tuned to a Conſonancy, and the String of one be ſtruck, the ſame ſtring of the other will ſound, though laid at a Diſtance; ſuch an Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony there is of Souls, that if a well-tuned Heart be ſtruck with the Finger of God, it will ſend forth ſuch a Melody that will work in others, an Uniſon, and Concord with it ſelf; <hi>Dauid</hi> went up with the Tribes to worſhip, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> brought <hi>Simon, Philip Nathaniel,</hi> the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Samaria</hi> the City of <hi>Sychar</hi> to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the <hi>Meſsiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did triumph in the Myriads of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Kingdoms of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the Numberleſs Acceſſions of the World to the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Flock of Chriſt. A <hi>Form</hi> well ordered in all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35139:16"/> things by a ſweet and gracious Converſation, doth powerfully and placidly inſinuate it ſelf to produce this Effect; which I ſhall demonſtrate thus. The Word is the great Inſtrument of Faith; it hath a Moral, and Suaſive Power to propound Arguments to the Underſtanding, and Objects to the Will, <hi>Faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</hi> But this Cauſe is not irreſiſtible, for we find the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> taking up the Complaint of the <hi>Prophet, Who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved our report?</hi> But where the Word is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, the <hi>Form</hi> of a good Converſation may be Efficient of Faith in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts <hi>Wives</hi> to be in ſubjection to their own <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, that if any obey not the Word, they may without the Word be won, with the converſation of their Wives, while they behold their chaſtity cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled with fear.</hi> It ſeems the Eye is a better Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan then the Ear, ſometimes to conveigh Light and Happineſs to the Spirit, and good Works are better Orators then good Words; For ſo we read in Story, that <hi>Theodolinda,</hi> Queen of the <hi>Longobards,</hi> converted both her Husbands, the Firſt from <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> the other from <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> an auſpicious Lady, to eſpouſe them both to the great Bridegroom of Souls; but the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:35139:16"/> is ſtill Big with greater Wonder, for her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues were ſo Exemplary and Eminent, that they executed an Apoſtolick Office, and converted the Nation of her Subjects to be baptized into the Catholick Faith.</p>
               <p>If thou ſeeſt a beauty in the <hi>Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and wouldſt preſerve it from decay, avoid the ſins mentioned in the Catalogue. The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of a <hi>form,</hi> are thoſe of her own houſe, no Sins make her more Odious, then thoſe that are Shrowded and Sheltred under her Protection.</p>
               <p>All ſin hath ſuch an abhorrence to the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of holineſs, that they hate the <hi>Form,</hi> and Fringes of her Garment (as is commonly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Panther, that he ſo abhors the perſon of a man, that he tears in pieces his picture) For a <hi>Form</hi> extorts, from Seducers, and Sectaries, thoſe Actions that are againſt the Bent and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of their hearts; They are Covetous, and yet the falſe Apoſtles at <hi>Corinth,</hi> preached freely to get Occaſion of Glory, and diſgrace St. <hi>Paul;</hi> who was there forced to live by his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Labours, that he might not be Burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, or Chargeable to that Opulent and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious City.</p>
               <p>They are Self-lovers, in their Benificence and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35139:17"/> Good Will towards men. I need not mention anymore, ſeeing Self-love is ſo Prolifical a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of all the other Sins, that they muſt have a Commixture and Co-incidence with it, as Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Stem from whence they grow: So that the <hi>Form</hi> is a Reſtriction to, and Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Villanies, though they uſe it as an Artifice to palliate their ſweet and ſecret Sins, and to make way for an open Diſſolution; <hi>The ſixth verſe</hi> calls them <hi>Creepers, while they creep into houſes unawares, and privily ſow their Tares,</hi> and are Deſpicable; they inſinuate themſelves with Pretences of Strictneſs, and a Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, of Modeſty, and Meekneſs, of Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions, and Philanthropy; but when the Creeping Party becomes prevailing, they ſoon forget their formal Complements, and break the Bonds of their former Reſtrictions aſunder, and caſt away their Cords from them; they are Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, and fill heaven with Reproaches; Traytors, and fill Kingdoms with Seditions, the Tender Conſcience ſoon betrayes it ſelf in Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and unnatural Affection, is incontinent in all Exceſſes, and fierce in all Errors, with a Rage reaching up to heaven: how contrary is this to the Light of the Goſpel, that is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35139:17"/> Serene, and Pacifical; to the Tongues of Fire that deſcended on the Apoſtles, that by all-powerfull words did create thoſe Miracles that were all like his that ſent the Comforter, the inſtances of mercy: new light ſoon turns into Wild-fire, and the Tender Conſcience Ravens as a Wolfe, to make havock of the Church; The <hi>Arians,</hi> and <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of old, and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> in <hi>Munſter,</hi> and <hi>Sectaries</hi> of <hi>England</hi> of late have been ſufficient Arguments to make this manifeſt to all men, and Alarms to Princes whoſe ſecurity conſiſts in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Religion; In this vigilancy <hi>Babilon</hi> exceeded <hi>Zion,</hi> for <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> made a Decree, that <hi>what ever Nation ſpake againſt the God of Shadrach, ſhould be made a Dunghill,</hi> but of <hi>Judah</hi> where God was known the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> complains, <hi>according to the Number of thy Cities, ſo are thy Gods O Judah:</hi> to return, An Hypocrite Loves not freely, and heartily his Reigning Sin, becauſe it exerciſeth a Tyranny and Co-active Power over him; it reſtraines him from ſwallowing the ſweet Morcels he tacitely hungers after, therefore he Dethrones it, and takes away the Scepter of Authority from it, when he can have his other Lords to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35139:18"/> Reign over him; and expoſes his <hi>Form</hi> when he hath caſt of its Yoak to the greateſt Odium and Contempt; what cheap thoughts muſt men have of a <hi>Form of Godlineſs</hi> when it's infected with Diſhoneſty, the feigned Saint is manifeſtly a real Knave, and all his Humiliations and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, wherein he deprecates the Evils of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, are apparently but feigned words to make merchandiſe of the Inheritance of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, the Houſes of Widdowes, the Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Church, and the Rights of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? how infamous muſt the way of Balaam be in the opinions of men? who ſaid he would not curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> for an houſe-full of Silver and Gold; crying out, <hi>how good are thy Tents O Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and thy Tabernacles O Iſrael;</hi> Praying <hi>that there might be no Divination againſt Jacob, or Inchantment againſt Iſrael;</hi> yet all this holy Diſcourſe and heavenly Reſolution was but a Varniſh to a deceitfull heart that was Brib'd with filthy Lucre, and the Wages of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: can a Dogs neck more deſecrate an Altar? or the image of an <hi>Adonis</hi> a Temple? then for a man to fling out his Invectives againſt ſin, and yet to indulge thoſe that are contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to his Luſt, and Avarice? what are the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35139:18"/> Prayers of theſe men but ſo many Practical Lyes told to heaven, who while they pray, with a tacite Blaſphemy defie God, and when they ſin, by open Atheiſm deny him, and the Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are as certainly the Captives of the Devil, as they are the creatures of God.</p>
               <p>Avoid thoſe ſins that are inconſiſtent with a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> which may be reduced to a tripartite Diviſion; Some hinder the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a <hi>Form,</hi> others Blaſt it, whilſt it is Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed; and others do Renounce it, and Caſt it off. The ſins that hinder the Aſſuming of a <hi>Form,</hi> are <hi>Prejudice,</hi> and <hi>Fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt the Precepts, that command us to cut off the Right hand, which is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Mutilation of the Body; as Fervency of Spirit is the Calenture of the Soul, the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating and Doing good, the Waſting the Eſtate, and being Evil ſpoken of for the Name of Chriſt, the Wounding the Reputation, theſe are the Grievous Commandments of an Hard Maſter, to which, in ſtead of Binding them to mens Fingers, they give them a Manumiſſion; and with the Young man in the Goſpel, Go away; and with <hi>Orpah,</hi> ſalute, and forſake to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35139:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fear,</hi> if with <hi>Scylla,</hi> they could ſee a Crown on the Liver of the Sacrifice, the Wages of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the Divinations of Riches and Honour; they would become Diſciples; but when they Obſerve all that will live Godly in Chriſt, muſt ſuffer Perſecution, and through many Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we muſt enter into the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they are offended at the Croſs of Chriſt, they think there is a Lyon in the way, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightens them from any Eſſay of walking in them.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſins hinder men from being Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, but which is worſe, ſome that are Baptized blaſt their Profeſſion by a Flagitious Life, live without God in the world, that it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them they had never known the Way of Truth. Such are they that think it below a Brave Spirit, to tremble at a Threatning, but ſtifle the Warnings of their own Boſom, and live in Chambering, and Wantonneſs, Rage, and Riot, Swearing, and Uncleanneſs, that a man without the Breach of Charity may ſay, they have no Faith.</p>
               <p>But Apoſtacy, from Faith, and Obedience, does Obliterate all the Characters of a <hi>Form,</hi> and makes Shipwrack of Profeſſion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35139:19"/> Communion with the Viſible Church. There were three ſorts of theſe <hi>Apoſtates</hi> in the times of St. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> the <hi>Traditores,</hi> that gave their Bibles, in ſtead of their Bodies, to be burnt; the <hi>Thurificati,</hi> that offered Incenſe to Idols; and the <hi>Libellatici,</hi> whoſe Denials of Chriſt were more Private and Auricular, but bought Tickets from the Magiſtrates, to preſerve them from that Bloody Inquiſition. Now an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate cannot be an Hypocrite, for he is gone out of the Precincts of the Church; <hi>They went out from us, becauſe they were not of us, ſaith St. John,</hi> they have broken themſelves off from that Body into which they were implanted by Baptiſm, and are Strangers to the Covenant of Promiſe: Thus we ſee the Dignity, and Defection of a <hi>Form,</hi> how it is to be exerciſed, ſuſpended, and moderated, and how to direct its courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Rude, and Rigid Zeal, and a looſe and Sceptical Profeſſion; we ſee the Grounds and Gradations of its Diſhonours, and Decays, how that it departs from ſome men as the Glory of the Lord did from the Temple, and Altar, and Threſhold of the houſe, in the Viſion of <hi>Ezekiel:</hi> and when the Leafe thus falls and withereth, the Tree is Barren, and Corrupt,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35139:20"/> for that is the Climacterical time to ſhew its Diſeaſe is Mortal, and therefore it muſt not cumber the Vineyard, but be cut down, or plucked up by the Rootes.</p>
               <p>But it is high time for us to come to the <hi>Power of Godlineſs,</hi> which hath ſo much Goodneſs in it, that it ſhould not be accounted an Offence; and ſo much Wiſdom, that it ſhould not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Fooliſhneſs; the Neceſſity of it is ſo great, that it ſhould not be Delayed, and the Excellency ſo Glorious, that it ſhould not be Denied: therefore, as all men ſhould acquire it for Salvation, ſo our Preſent Duty is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, wherein it Conſiſts, and Diſcovereth it ſelf.</p>
               <p>I have already explained the Phraſe, that the Reducing of the Habits, and Vital Principles of Grace into Act, is the <hi>Power of Godlineſs;</hi> the Philoſophy of which Leads us to the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That Habits of Grace are thoſe Divine Qualities, infuſed into the Soul by the Spirit of God, which incline the Heart, and ſway the Conſcience to an actual Obedience, to the Will of God, with Facility, and great Delight. They are therefore called by the Fathers, and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Springs, and Fountains of Grace, not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35139:20"/> like the Fountain in the midſt of Paradiſe that flowes with continual waters, but like the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Siloam, that ſpring from the foot of mount Sion, <hi>qui non jugibus aequis ſed certis horis diebuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ebullit,</hi> whoſe Streams are not alwayes Current, but in the due ſeaſons of time: The muſical knowledge of a Lutaniſt in his Quavers, Reſts, and Motions, whereby he is able on all occaſions to play thoſe delightfull <hi>Airs</hi> that commend his skill, is the Habit of the Artiſt, but ſuppoſe the Hand of the Lutaniſt be wounded, he hath ſtill the knowledge, and Habit of his Faculty, although the Exerciſe be prevented by the Indiſpoſition of that neceſſary Inſtrument of his muſick; ſo the Godly man that hath theſe principles of a Celeſtial Original, hath upon all occaſions his ſences exerciſed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of uſe, ſutable to thoſe commands the law of God requires, and thoſe Emergencies the Providences of God expoſe him to: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Acts of Grace may be ſuſpended ſometimes by Natural, or Civil actions, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by inevitable Infirmities, yet ſtill he hath a New Nature, the Unction of the Holy one, and the ſeed of God abiding in him: for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35139:21"/> our clearer underſtanding of which, we are to conſider.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Plenty of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> conſiſts in the Habits of Graces; The Righteous are ſaid to be <hi>Trees Planted by the Rivers of water,</hi> and <hi>the Trees of the Lord are full of Sappe.</hi> The Radical moyſture of theſe noble Vines may Retire to the Root in Winter, yet at the return of the Sun they ſend forth their Grapes in Cluſters, and their Perfume as the ſmell of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon, as a homage of gratitude to the Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Heaven, and the Bleſſings of God. Theſe are the Gifts of a Liberal God, like thoſe of a Prince in his Inauguration and Feſtivity, for he ſheds abroad the waſhing of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the renewing of the Holy Ghoſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly upon us; that we may abound in the work of the Lord. And as there is more light in the body of the Sun, then in all the beams that ſhine on the World; for, ſuppoſe they were all Eclipſed, the Sun in a moment, or impercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible time, could ſupply them all, by one Irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation; ſo if the Acts of Grace were all vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they would be Renewed by the treaſures of their Cauſes. The Acts of Grace are Tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but the Habits are Permanent, and Reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35139:21"/> the ſoul with innumerable Activities, to the Comfort of the Believer, and the Glory of the Giver. This is called, a Living by Faith, therefore acts flow from the Habits of grace, as beams from the Sun, and ſtreams from a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, are many, mighty, pleaſing, vigorous, and delectable, they are free, frequent, natural, and numberleſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Power of Godlineſs,</hi> is the reducing the Habits of Grace into Exerciſe, and Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ſame word doth the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> uſe to his <hi>ſon Timothy, Be ſtrong in the Grace that is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; go on from Strength to Strength, till thou appear before God in Sion;</hi> ſhine like the Sun, more and more, till the perfect Day, who from the Twylight of the morning, Runs his Race like a <hi>Gyant,</hi> till it comes to its meridian brightneſs. The Initials of Grace are weak, like an Embryo, infirm as an Infant, but by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded acts, the Smoaking Flax is kindled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Flame, and the Bruiſed Reed becomes a Cedar, the Habits grow in ſtrength, and ſtature, by the addition of one grace to another, which is the ſupply of every part extenſively, adding to faith virtue; and intenſively, by the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one degree of Grace unto another, till it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35139:22"/> comes to the meaſure of its ſtature; when righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is revealed from faith to faith; Grace is never commenſurate in the beauty of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till it is conſummate in the beauty of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. They that were divorced from their ſins, as <hi>Phaltiel</hi> was from <hi>Michal,</hi> who went weeping after her to <hi>Bahurim;</hi> when this Gift of God is ſtirred up in them, contemplate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs with joy; they that did deprecate Wrath with Fear, implore Mercy with Confidence; They that ſought after him whom their ſoul Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when, with <hi>Andrew,</hi> they have found the Meſſias, Lean on his boſom, Love him dearly, Eſteem him highly, Follow him fully, and Live with him eternally.</p>
               <p>The weak in the faith, and the feeble-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wreſtle not with Principalities, and Powers, but with God himſelf, give all diligence to make their Calling ſure, preſs forward to the Price of their high Calling, abound in the work of the Lord, till by unceſſant Labours, they reſt in the Fruition of him; as if we might ſuppoſe a ſpark of Fire unextinguiſhable, it would be in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Aſcents, till it came to its own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and Region, under the Concave of the Moon</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35139:22"/>1. There is a mighty Tendency and Impulſe in Habits to exert themſelves into Act, they are the full Breaſts of Conſolation, that are uneaſie till they are Drawn, and Diſpenced, they are as ſeed caſt into the Earth, that lives and growes up into an Harveſt; They are Talents to be improved, and Lamps to be furniſhed; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Flames are ſoon ſpent unleſs God be in the Buſh, and Streams ſoon vaniſh without an Ocean, it being God that worketh in us both to Will, and to Doe, that giveth Life and Motion to theſe Qualities of the Soul; we muſt have ſtill Recourſe to the Influences of his Power, and the ſupplyes of his ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a Gratitude in free and frequent acts to further the Growth, Strength, and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of their Habits; as natural Qualities are intended by natural Actions, ſo are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, as the more a man playes on a Muſical Inſtrument, the greater are the habiliments of his art; So <hi>Hoſeah.</hi> 6.3. Then ſhall ye know the Lord, if ye follow on to know the Lord; infuſed knowledge ſhould be increaſed by a ſtudious meditation; So <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Filled with the Knowledge of his will in all wiſdom and ſpiritual underſtanding,</hi> there is the Infuſion of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35139:23"/> the Habit, <hi>That ye might walk worthy of the Lord unto all well pleaſing, being fruitfull in every good work,</hi> there it is reduced to act, <hi>increaſing in the knowledge of God,</hi> there is the Radication of it, <hi>For he that will do Gods will ſhall know of the Doctrine whether it be of God. Joh.</hi> 17.7. they are not Lazy and Languid things, but are diſcovered by the facility ſtrengthned by the frequency of their own Actions. The habit and the act are thus bound up together in the Bundles of life, combine in Vigor, and Virtue, in Influence, and Cauſality on one another; and hence it is that an Habit of Grace is a Quality difficultly removed, and although it may be interrupted and ſuſpended by impetuous Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and imperious Luſts, yet in this Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Conflict it is Reſtleſs till it is prevalent, and have Dominion, as the Sympathy of a Needle touched with a Load-ſtone makes it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet in its greateſt trembling, and diſturbance, till it Reſts, as in its Center, in a Direct Line poynting at the Polar ſtar; And as in an uneven Ally a Bowl may run one way when the Byaſs inclines it another, ſo a Godly Man may be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by Surreption and Infirmity, though the Habit doth ſublimate, and ſway the heart to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35139:23"/> ſervice of God: The habits of Grace will not be kept <hi>in arctâ cuſtodiâ,</hi> but will break priſon, and walk at Liberty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This <hi>Power</hi> diſcovereth it ſelf.</head>
               <p n="1">1. In Reſiſting ſtrong Temptations, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it in the Alluſion of the Apoſtle, it quits it ſelf like a Man in its ſpiritual Olympicks, when the meſſenger of Satan buffeted our Apoſtle he beſought the Lord thrice, the aſſault of an Enemy excites the valour of a Veteran Souldier, ſo the urgency and vehemency of Temptation made him ingeminate his requeſts to God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In mortifying ſtrong corruptions, dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Satan from his ſtrong holds, captivating every Imagination, that towreth againſt the commands of Chriſt, deſtroying every Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin, as <hi>Joſuah</hi> did the Kings of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In Acts of eminent Obedience; A ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice can be worth but little, that coſts nothing; <hi>Abel</hi> offered up his Beſt, <hi>Abraham</hi> was willing to ſacrifice his ſon, St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be offered; This <hi>Power</hi> animates and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obles the heart, to hate father, and mother, to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35139:24"/> caſt away his chiefeſt Joy, as a ſnare, to cut off the Right hand, and pull out the Right eye, to fling away the moſt precious Treaſure, as a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at the command of Chriſt; if a man have Wit and Learning, this divine power is as a ſpring of Motion to him, to be uſefull and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in worthy Inſtances, and Inſtitutions; in meditations on Gods Word, Defence of his Truth, Inſtruction of his People, and inquiry into thoſe myſteries, that is, the Emulation of Angels to pry into: if a man hath Honour, this Power makes it a Champion for the Patronage, and Luſtre of Religion, it Humbles him, to fling down his Coronet at the feet of the Lamb, and Advanceth him, becauſe he hath ſomething the world hath an Eſteem for, to Deny for his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, which is beyond the Proportions, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities of ordinary Chriſtians: if he hath Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, this <hi>Power</hi> turns his Almoner, feeds the Hungry, cloaths the Naked, Erects Hoſpitals, builds Schools of Learning, and makes his life the definition of the Law of Charity: all his meaſures in religion are laudable, and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, not onely thruſt down, and ſhaken toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but running over.</p>
               <p>But do not theſe Gloryes of the <hi>Power</hi> of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35139:24"/> 
                  <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> diſcourage thoſe that are weak in grace? I anſwer, that it may be propounded as a Probleme, that the New-born Babe hath more ſtrength, then the Old man, the infancy of grace is more powerfull, then the Decrepid Age of an inveterate Luſt, as there is more vigour in a few Drops of <hi>Spirits,</hi> then a great quantity of water; ſo there is in the ſmalleſt ſeed, and ſparkle of Godlineſs, then the greater meaſures of Corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption: for this ſeed grows in the midſt of all the Tares that would choak it, and this ſparkle lives in the midſt of all the waters that would extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it, and the ſmoaking Flax, and bruiſed Reed, break forth into Victory, againſt all the Winds and Tempeſts that oppoſe them: which ſtrange vigour doth not ariſe from the immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of any Grace in it ſelf, but from the ſupplies of that ſpirit, that is greater, <hi>potentior,</hi> ſaith <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> ſtronger in us, then he that is in the world.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude all by an inſtance, how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Habit of Love, that Powerful, and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Grace into act; which when it is once Kindled in the Boſom of a man, he finds his Heart, like the <hi>Diſciples</hi> going to <hi>Emaus,</hi> burn in the flames of a moſt Seraphical Affection. The <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Sentences</hi> denies any habit of Love in the ſoul, but aſſerts, that all its Emanations
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35139:25"/> flow immediately from the Perſon of the Holy Ghoſt: but ſeeing the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> expreſsly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth between the habit of Love, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as between the Effect, and its Cauſe, when he tells us, <hi>That the Love of God is ſhed abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our Hearts, by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and the Acts of this Love are Defined to be, <hi>the Fulfilling of the Law, the Bond of Perfection, and the end of the Commandment,</hi> we may reduce this habit into act by <hi>Examples,</hi> and <hi>Arguments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By <hi>Argument,</hi> Enter then, O my ſoul, into thoſe Galleries, wherein the King of Glory Walks, and is Detained; and Obſerve how he hath commended his Love toward thee, All the Dimenſions of his Love, its Height, Length, Depth, and Breadth are ſo many Topicks to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and allure thee, to be Eſpouſed to him, as thy Bridegroom.</p>
               <p>The heighth of this Love is Extaſie; that God over all, bleſſed for ever, equal to the Father, in whom are hid all the Treaſures of wiſdom, and Knowledge, whom the Angels worſhip, ſhould have his heart Raviſhed with a Creature, pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Blood, defiled with Sin, ſubjected to Damnation, that when thou waſt upon the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice of Ruine, ſtretched forth his hand to ſave thee, and draw thee into his Boſom. Canſt thou,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35139:25"/> O my ſoul! forbear to ſay with the <hi>beloved Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple; To him that Loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, and hath made us Kings, and Prieſts unto God; To him be glory and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The depth of this Love was humility, he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf to aſſume our nature in the Form of a ſervant, to bear our miſeries, and become obedient to death. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> were a famous pair of Lovers; <hi>Jonathan,</hi> who was heir apparent to the Crown, Knew <hi>David</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for it by the Almighty, yet was faithful to him in his ſecrets, ſollicitous for him in his Dangers, and gave him his hand to advance him to his own Throne: But the Love of Chriſt is without a Parallel, That ſupream power ſhould aſſume the Form of a Servant, infinite glory ſhould ſubmit to a Reproach, exquiſite Purity, ſhould ſuffer imputed ſin, that the Son of God's Complacency ſhould bear the Viols of his Wrath, ſhould deſcend from heaven, come out of the Boſom of his Father, to enter into a Grave; what greater token of his Love could he give thee, then his Agony, his Blood, his Life? Surely, O my ſoul, thou art harder then Iron, if this Loadſtone will not draw thee. Well might <hi>Solomon</hi> rifle all the Rarities of Nature, to be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35139:26"/> Symbols of this Love, to which the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not ſufficient to be an Allegory. For greater Love then this hath no man, then to Lay down his Life for his friend; but herein he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his Love to us, that while we were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, he died for us. Conſider the High Prieſt of our Profeſſion, hanging on the Altar of his Croſs, with his arms ſtretched wide open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thee, and canſt thou forbear Leaning on his Breaſt, and prying into the ſecrets of his Love, the Knowledge of which paſſeth Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>The Breadth of this Love is Univerſality: ſo immenſe it is, that it hath mercy for thouſands, a Plenteous Redemption, ſalvation to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt; he taſted death for every man, and Laid down his life for the world. No man ever peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for want of Bounty, or Bowels, the Paſſion or Compaſſion of a Saviour, but becauſe his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Part is offended at Chriſts Croſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Conſider then, O my ſoul! how dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable are his Laws? how glorious his Croſs? Obedience is eſſential to Love, and where it is habitual, there is as much Pleaſantneſs in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, as there is Sweetneſs in his Promiſe: if thou prefer profit with <hi>Judas,</hi> pleaſure with <hi>Zimri,</hi> honour with <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> an Obliquity before a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35139:26"/> Right path, thou doſt not only ſin againſt the Precept, but the Grace of God that would aſſiſt thee to obſerve it. Faith looks at a future Retribution, but love immediately at the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Law-giver and the kindneſs of his Commands; and if the Amabilities of them, were once preſented to thee, it would be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to thee to be vicious, as it would be to a vicious Perſon to be Devout; thou wouldſt ſee Liberty in his Yoake, and Lightneſs in his Burden, it would be as a Wing to a Dove, an help in motion, as Ballaſt to a ſhip, an hindrance againſt fluctuation. As his Commands are Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs, ſo is his Croſs peace, our Saviour to commend his Love to us, conſulted not the Dignity of his perſon, the Tragedy of his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but longed for his Suffrings, thirſted after his Cup, hungred after that Paſſover, which he was to eate with ſuch bitter herbs. Eſteem then O my Soul! but all things as Droſs to know the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, which are Seals of thy Adoption, Pledges of Gods pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Love, and and work an eternal weight of Glory.</p>
               <p>The length of this Love is eternity, its an antient Love, from everlaſting, he loved us firſt; its durable to everlaſting, he loved us to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:35139:27"/> the end; it is not Critical, or Captious to take offence at every lapſe, or Omiſſion. And if it be lawfull to ſpeak of the Duration of God, by the Meaſures of time; this Love was as great in the firſt Moment as it can be to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for then did the admirable and aſtoniſhing Wiſdom of the bleſſed Trinity conſult the Salvation of thy Precious Soul; by the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and Paſſion of the Son of God, when the fallen Angels were left in a State of irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable Perdition: That he that is Glorious in holineſs, ſhould be a Sin and a Curſe for us by the Projects ſet up from everlaſting, is ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious a Depth that unleſs it had been mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the Goſpel, had been the higheſt Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy to imagine it, and what the Wiſdom of the three Perſons did contrive, the Love of the ſecond did beſtow, he loved us, and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for us, Thou muſt then O my Soul! either account all this a Golden Dream, or a well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed Fable, or elſe not ſuffer the world to be a Rival in thy Eſtimation, and Affection with the Son of God, if theſe meditations be ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beleived, and judiciouſly weighed, thou canſt not Expoſtulate <hi>what is thy Beloved more then another Beloved, who is the cheifeſt among
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35139:27"/> ten thouſand, altogether Love, and altogether Lovely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Converſe with divine Objects and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. As Flame Kindles Flame, ſo doe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples excite Love, and Objects not only Attract the heart but Raviſh and Transform it; if <hi>David</hi> muſes, the fire will burn, if <hi>Moſes</hi> be in the mount his face will ſhine; the Butterfly doth adorn her ſelf, and the Bee enrich her ſelf, by dwelling on the Flowers of the feild; if a Ray of Love may ſpring from a Glance, how much more from a Viſion face to face, a full contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the beauty of holineſs? I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider but three freinds of the Bridegroom, and their Delicious Intimacies with him; <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> ſhe loved much, and kiſsed the feet of Chriſt, to acknowledge her ſubjection to him, ſhe waſhed them with her Tears, and wiped them with the Haires of her head: if there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re virtue in touching the Hemme of his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, much more in kiſſing his feet that were ſo Beautifull that his very foot-ſtool was glorious, and the Throne of Grace; St. <hi>John</hi> (we may ſay) kiſsed the hands of Chriſt to acknowledge his Dependance on him, whoſe hand was the great inſtrument of Bounty,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35139:28"/> whoſe Boſom, in which he Lodged, the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of Grace and Cabinet of ſecrets, where he had the miſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven revealed to him; could a man chooſe a diviner manſion, or inhabite a better Tabernacle? The Spouſe kiſſed the Lipps of Chriſt to ſhow her Communion with him. Thoſe Lipps that had Grace powred into them, and ſpake the Words of eternal Life; ſuch Examples will excite the heart to Emulation and make it ſick of Love; I will give him then ten thouſand Kiſſes, and embraces, I will ſerve him, praiſe him, Truſt in him till my love is conſummate, by being for ever with the Lord; And then O my Soul, if he ſhould aske thee as he did <hi>Peter, Simon Bar Jonah Loveſt thou me?</hi> thou wilt anſwer as he did, <hi>Lord, thou knoweſt all things, thou knowest that I love thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this inſtance we are directed to exerciſe any other Grace of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35139:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
